<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://www.sosdg.org/~stephanie/css/docbook/driver.css" type="text/css"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <title>EFNet Spamtrap</title>

  <subtitle>A guide to EFNet's spamtrap system for End Users</subtitle>

  <articleinfo>
    <date>$Date: 2007-01-07 15:04:50 -0500 (Sun, 07 Jan 2007) $</date>

    <author>
      <firstname>Stephanie</firstname>

      <surname>Daugherty</surname>

      <othername>(Triona)</othername>

      <affiliation>
        <jobtitle>IRC Operator</jobtitle>

        <orgname>irc.efnet.nl</orgname>
      </affiliation>
    </author>

    <releaseinfo>$Id: spamtrap.xml 10 2007-01-07 20:04:50Z Stephanie $ </releaseinfo>

    <copyright>
      <year>2007</year>
    </copyright>

    <othercredit>
      <contrib>Thanks to ^duck^, Beige, HndlWCare, wmono, Jupiter, jilles, and
      various other EFNet opers and #irchelp'ers for proofreading and
      feedback.</contrib>
    </othercredit>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>This document is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-No
      Derivative Works 2.5 License which can be reviewed at <ulink
      url="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/</ulink>.</para>
    </legalnotice>
  </articleinfo>

  <section>
    <title id="overview">Overview - What is Spamtrap?</title>

    <para>Spamtrap is a sophisticated, distributed system run by EFNet IRC
    Operators and Administrators to detect spambots. It helps EFNet detect and
    respond to spambots proactively - often before they would be detected by a
    user complaint or by server-level spam detection.</para>

    <para>The system is flexible, and under constant change and improvement to
    improve detection rates and keep the system as unobtrusive as possible
    while maintaining our goals of <link linkend="privacy">protecting
    privacy</link>, efficient use of resources, proactively catching spambots,
    and preventing <link linkend="falsepos">false positives</link>.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title id="how">How does spamtrap work?</title>

    <para>Spamtrap uses a set of honeypots that roam the network to bait
    spambots. Messages received by the honeypots (also referred to as "spam
    collectors") are analyzed to determine if they are spam, and if so, what
    action should be taken.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title id="privacy">How is privacy protected?</title>

    <para>The spamtrap system only cares about messages and invitations
    specifically addressed to the collectors. Conversations within channels
    simply aren't processed by the system.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title id="falsepos">Will spamtrap mistake legitimate onjoin messages for
    spam? What do I do if I believe I've been banned unfairly?</title>

    <para>Probably not. If this happens at all, it happens very rarely. We
    respect that channels may wish to legitimately use onjoin messages to
    convey information to their users, and recognize that such messages may
    legitimately contain URLs and similar information. Spamtrap has a number
    of measures to differentiate between legitimate onjoin messages and spam.
    There have been very few reports of false positives from onjoin messages,
    and we take all reports of false positives seriously.</para>

    <para>All automaticly generated K: lines (bans) from the spamtrap system
    include a support URL with pointers to help and a tracking code that an
    IRC operator can use to find full details of what triggered the ban.
    Please include the full ban message when asking for help regarding a
    spamtrap K: line or G: line.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title id="goaway">The spamtrap collectors are annoying, how can I keep them out of my
    channel?</title>

    <para>While we try to keep the system as unobtrusive as possible, our
    privacy obligations and the technical limitations of IRC itself mean that
    you will sometimes notice a spamtrap collector joining or leaving a
    channel. The last thing we want is to create a greater nuisance than the
    one we are trying to correct.</para>

    <para>If you are a channel operator for a particular channel, there are a
    few possibilities.</para>

    <para>As the main way we find channels to patrol is from /list, setting a
    channel +s and keeping it that way will usually stop the spamtrap system
    from checking that channel for spam. Unless the channel has been
    identified as a "priority channel", the spamtrap collectors will stop
    coming within a few hours, and will leave the channel alone as long as it
    is +s. For many channels, this is the best solution, because it also makes
    it harder for spambots to find your channels.</para>

    <para>If you don't wish to set +s, or if the channel is already +s, you
    can ask for assistance in <ulink
    url="irc://irc.efnet.org/spamfix">#spamfix</ulink>, and we will discuss
    the matter and work with you to find a solution which may include
    excluding the channel from spamtrap or reducing the frequency with which
    spamtrap's collectors join your channel.</para>

    <para>While we can't stop you from banning the collectors from your
    channels, we don't recommend doing so because the hostmasks are changed
    constantly, and there are easier solutions described above.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title id="help">I'm having problems with spambots in my channel, Can
    spamtrap help?</title>

    <para>Remember that spamtrap only deals with spam that's delivered
    privately. If the spam is happening in channel, spamtrap can't help.
    Report any spambots you see to an IRC operator - preferably on the same
    server as the spambot.</para>

    <note>
      <para><link linkend="privacy">Because spamtrap does not process channel
      conversations</link>, it won't catch spambots that join a channel and
      spam in the channel. We have other means of detecting these type of
      spambots, however, if you see one please report them to an IRC Operator
      or to <ulink url="irc://irc.efnet.org/spamfix">#spamfix</ulink> so that
      we can ensure they are addressed quickly.</para>
    </note>

    <para>If the spambots are using private message, notices, etc, an IRC
    operator may be able to adjust spamtrap's settings for your channel to
    improve it's effectiveness - if necessary we can force spamtrap to visit a
    channel more often.</para>

    <para>If your channel is very small, or +s, spamtrap may not find it
    without help - if spambots plague such a channel, <link
    linkend="support">feel free to ask for assistance</link> in <ulink
    url="irc://irc.efnet.org/spamfix">#spamfix</ulink>.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="support">
    <title>Where can I find more information or support?</title>

    <para>To keep the system as effective as possible, we have to chosen to
    limit the available information. Spammers are known to use any information
    available to improve the effectiveness of their spambots. We already have
    seen dramatic changes in the way spambots on EFNet behave, and this can be
    attributed at least in part to the spamtrap system. Please understand that
    we do not wish to aid spammers in any way, and that we have to be vague in
    some of our descriptions and with the details we do release.</para>

    <para>Also due to these concerns, we do not post any listing of the
    spamtrap collectors and their hostmasks or discuss their numbers, and we
    strongly discourage others from doing so - such lists make our efforts to
    fight spam more difficult, while providing little benefit to anyone, since
    we change the hostmasks constantly.</para>

    <para>With that said, we maintain the <ulink
    url="irc://irc.efnet.org/spamfix">#spamfix</ulink> channel on EFNet for
    users to go for help with spam issues or issues with the spamtrap
    system.</para>
  </section>
</article>